<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! trunk/opendj3/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011-2015 ForgeRock AS.
  !
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-intro'
         xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
         xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
         xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook
                             http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
         xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'>
 <title>Introduction to Deployment Planning</title>

 <para>The OpenAM Deployment Planning Guide presents the key features and
  possible solutions to protect your Identity and Access Management (IAM) deployments.
  The guide discusses the benefits and advantages of implementing OpenAM. It also
  provides examples of deployment to help you determine which features you might
  want to include in your deployments.
 </para>


 <section xml:id="understanding-iam">
  <title>Understanding Identity Access Management</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>Identity Access Management</primary>
   <secondary>understanding</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>The proliferation of cloud-based technologies, mobile devices, social networks,
   Big Data, enterprise applications, and business-to-business (B2B) services has spurred
   the exponential growth of identity information, which is often stored in
   varied and widely-distributed identity environments.</para>

  <para>The challenges of securing such identity data and the environments that
   depend on the identity data are daunting.
   Organizations that expand their services in-house or globally through internal
   development or through acquisitions must manage identities across wide spectrum of
   identity infrastructures.
   This expansion requires a careful integration of acquisitions must manage
   identities across a wide spectrum of identity infrastructures.
   This expansion requires a careful integration of disparate access management
   systems, platform-dependent architectures with limited scalability, and ad-hoc
   security components.
  </para>

  <para>ForgeRock, a leader in the IAM market,
   provides proven solutions to securing your identity data with its
   Identity Relationship Management (IRM) platform.</para>

  <para>Identity Management is the automated
   provisioning, updating, and de-provisioning of identities over their lifecycles.
   Access Management is the authentication and authorization of identities
   who desire privileged access to an organization's resources.
   Access management encompasses the central auditing of operations
   performed on the system by customers, employees, and partners.
   Access management also provides the means to share identity data across
   different access management systems, legacy implementations, and networks.
  </para>
  </section>

 <section xml:id="not-just-sso">
  <title>OpenAM is More than Just Single Sign-On</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>OpenAM</primary>
   <secondary>described</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>Identity Relationship Management (IRM)</primary>
   <secondary>described</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>OpenAM is an all-in-one open source, centralized access management solution,
   securing protected resources across the network and providing authentication,
   authorization, Web security, and Federation Services in a single, integrated solution.
   OpenAM is deployed as a simple <literal>.war</literal> file and provides production-proven
   platform independence, flexible and extensible components, as well as a
   high availability and a highly scalable infrastructure.
   Using open standards, OpenAM is fully extensible, and can expand its
   capabilities through its SDKs and numerous REST endpoints.
  </para>

  <para>OpenAM is part of ForgeRock's Identity Relationship Management (IRM)
   <emphasis>platform</emphasis>, built upon ForgeRock's Open Identity Stack,
   an open source identity and access management provider of mobile-ready,
   cloud, enterprise, social, and partner services.
   The IRM platform provides global consumer services across any platform for
   any connected device or any Internet-connected entity.
  </para>

  <para>ForgeRock IRM platform features the following products:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para><emphasis role="bold">OpenAM Context-Based Access Management System</emphasis>.
      OpenAM is an all-in-one industry-leading access management solution,
      providing authentication, authorization, federation, Web services security,
      adaptive risk, and entitlements services among many other features.
      OpenAM is deployed as a simple <literal>.war</literal> file, featuring
      an architecture that is platform independent, flexible, and extensible, and
      highly available and scalable.
     </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para><emphasis role="bold">OpenIDM</emphasis>. Cloud-Focused Identity Administration.
      OpenIDM is a lightweight provisioning system, built on resource-oriented
      principles. OpenIDM is a self-contained system, providing workflow,
      compliance, synchronization, password management, and connectors. OpenIDM
      features a next-generation modular architecture that is self-contained and
      highly extensible.
     </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">OpenDJ</emphasis>. Internet Scale Directory Server.
     OpenDJ provides full LDAP protocol support, multi-protocol access, cross-domain
     replication, common REST framework, SCIM support, and many other features.
    </para>
   </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para><emphasis role="bold">OpenIG</emphasis>. No Touch Single Sign-On (SSO)
      to enterprise, legacy, and custom applications. OpenIG is a
      reverse proxy server with specialized session management and credential
      replay functionality. OpenIG works together with OpenAM to integrate Web
      applications without needing to modify the target application or the
      container that it runs in.
     </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para><emphasis role="bold">OpenICF</emphasis>. Enterprise and Cloud
      Identity Infrastructure Connectors. OpenICF provides identity provisioning
      connections offering a consistent layer between
      target resources and applications and exposing a set of programming functions
      for the full lifecycle of an identity. OpenICF connectors are compatible
      with OpenIDM, Sun Identity Manager, <trademark class="registered">Oracle</trademark>
      Waveset, <trademark class="registered">Brinqa</trademark> GRC Platform, and others.
     </para>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="figure-irm"/> illustrates the ForgeRock IRM platform.
     </para>
   </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

  <figure xml:id="figure-irm" >
   <title>ForgeRock IRM Platform</title>
   <mediaobject >
    <alt>IRM Platform</alt>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="images/forgerock-irm-dpg.png"
                format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
     <para>The IRM Platform features a highly modular and flexible architecture,
      centralizing identity and access management and securing protected resource
      across a widely-distributed network.</para>
    </textobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </section>

 <!-- This section was brought in from another chapter -->
 <section xml:id="am-server-overview">
  <title>OpenAM Server Overview</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>OpenAM</primary>
   <secondary>overview</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>OpenAM is an open source centralized access management server, securing
   protected resources across the network and providing authentication,
   authorization, Web security, and federation services in a single, integrated solution.
   OpenAM manages access to the protected resources by controlling who has access,
   when, how long, and under what conditions by centralizing disparate hardware and
   software services for cloud, enterprise, mobile, and business-to-business (B2B)
   systems.
  </para>

  <para>
   <xref linkend="figure-openam-apis"/> illustrates the OpenAM architecture.
  </para>

  <figure xml:id="figure-openam-apis" >
   <title>OpenAM Architecture</title>
   <mediaobject >
    <alt>OpenAM Architecture</alt>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="images/openam-architecture-dpg.png"
                format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
     <para>OpenAM has a highly modular and flexible architecture, centralizing
      access management and securing protected resource across the network.</para>
    </textobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>OpenAM features a highly modular and flexible architecture with
   multiple plug-in points to meet any customer deployment. It leverages industry
   standard protocols, such as HTTP, XML, SOAP, REST, SAML 2.0, OAuth 2.0, OpenID Connect 1.0,
   and others to deliver a high performance, highly scalable, and highly available
   access management solution over the network. OpenAM services are 100% Java-based, proven
   across multiple platforms and containers in many production deployments.</para>

  <para>OpenAM core server can be deployed and integrated within existing network
   infrastructures. OpenAM provides the following distribution files:</para>

  <?hard-pagebreak?>
  <table xml:id="table-openam-distribution-files">
   <title>OpenAM Distribution Files</title>
   <tgroup cols="4">
    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="2*"/>
    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="5*"/>
    <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="0.5*"/>
    <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" colwidth="0.5*"/>
    <thead>
     <row><?dbfo bgcolor="#EEEEEE" ?>
      <entry>Distribution</entry>
      <entry>Description</entry>
      <entry namest="col3" nameend="col4" align="center">Deploy ?</entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>Default</entry>
      <entry>
       OpenAM's default distribution
       <literal>.war</literal> file includes the core server code with an embedded OpenDJ directory
       server, which stores configuration data and simplifies deployments.
       The distribution includes an administrative graphical user
       interface (GUI) Web console. During installation, the <literal>.war</literal> file
       accesses a bootstrap file to obtain the fully qualified domain name, port,
       context path, and the location of the configuration folder.
      </entry>
      <entry>Y</entry>
      <entry>N</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Core Server Only</entry>
      <entry>
       OpenAM provides a core
       server-only <literal>.war</literal> file without the OpenAM Console.
       This setup is often used in multi-server deployments wherein the deployments
       is managed using a full server instance using the
       <command>ssoadm</command> command-line tool.
       The OpenAM server installs with an embedded OpenDJ directory server.
      </entry>
      <entry>Y</entry>
      <entry>N</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Identity Provider (IdP) Discovery Service</entry>
      <entry>OpenAM provides an IdP Discovery Profile (SAMLv2
       binding profile) for its IdP Discovery service.
       The profile keeps track of the identity providers for each user.
      </entry>
      <entry>Y</entry>
      <entry>N</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>OpenAM Client Java SDK</entry>
      <entry>
       OpenAM provides a smaller subset of the OpenAM SDK, providing
       client-side API to OpenAM services.
       The Client SDK allows you to write remote standalone or Web applications
       to access OpenAM and run its core services.
      </entry>
      <entry>Y</entry>
      <entry>N</entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </table>

  <para>
   ForgeRock's OpenAM product is built on open-source code.
   ForgeRock maintains the OpenAM product, providing the community an open-source
   code repository, issue tracking, mailing lists, Web sites, and continuous
   integration as well as nightly builds from the latest code.
   ForgeRock also provides commercial releases of fully tested builds.
   ForgeRock offers the services you need to deploy OpenAM commercial builds into
   production, including training, consulting, and support.</para>

 </section>

 <section xml:id="key-benefits">
  <title>OpenAM Key Benefits</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>OpenAM</primary>
   <secondary>key benefits</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
   The goal of OpenAM is to provide secure, low friction access to valued
   resources while presenting the user with a consistent experience.
   OpenAM provides excellent security, which is totally transparent to the user.
  </para>

  <para>
   OpenAM provides the following key benefits to your organization:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Enables Solutions for Additional Revenue
     Streams</emphasis>.
     OpenAM provides the tools and components to quickly deploy services
     to meet customer demand. For example,
     OpenAM's Federation Services supports quick and easy deployment with
     existing SAMLv2, OAuth2, and OpenID Connect systems. For systems that do not support
     a full SAMLv2 deployment, OpenAM provides a <emphasis>Fedlet</emphasis>,
     a small SAML 2.0 application, which lets service providers quickly add
     SAML 2.0 support to their Java or .NET applications. These solutions open
     up new possibilities for additional revenue streams.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Reduces Operational Cost and Complexity</emphasis>.
     OpenAM can function as a hub, leveraging existing identity
     infrastructures and providing multiple integration
     paths using its authentication, SSO, and policies to your
     applications without the complexity of sharing Web access tools and passwords
     for data exchange. OpenAM decreases the total cost of ownership (TCO) through
     its operational efficiencies, rapid time-to-market, and high scalability
     to meet the demands of our market.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Improves User Experience</emphasis>. OpenAM
     enables users to experience more services using SSO without
     the need of multiple passwords.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Easier Configuration and Management</emphasis>.
     OpenAM centralizes the configuration and management of your access management
     system, allowing easier administration through its console
     and command-line tools. OpenAM also features a flexible deployment
     architecture that unifies services through its modular and
     embeddable components. OpenAM provides a common REST framework and common
     user interface (UI) model, providing scalable solutions as your customer
     base increases to the hundreds of millions.
     OpenAM also allows enterprises to outsource IAM services to system
     integrators and partners.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Increased Compliance</emphasis>. OpenAM provides
     an extensive entitlements service, featuring attribute-based access control (ABAC)
     policies as its main policy framework with features like import/export support
     to XACML, a policy editor, and REST endpoints for policy management.
     OpenAM also includes an extensive auditing service
     to monitor access according to regulatory compliance standards.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="openam-history">
   <title>OpenAM History</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>OpenAM</primary>
   <secondary>history</secondary>
  </indexterm>

   <para>
    OpenAM began with Sun Microsystem's Sun Java System Portal Server,
    which was a component of the Sun Java System Enterprise Edition. The Portal
    Server became a standalone product called
    Sun Java System Access Manager, which also featured an Identity Management
    product when Sun acquired Waveset. Access Manager became OpenSSO.
   </para>

   <para>
    OpenAM's timeline is summarized as follows:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>In 2005, Sun announces OpenSSO based on the Sun Java System Access
      Manager.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>In 2008, Sun releases OpenSSO build 6, a community open-source version
      and OpenSSO Enterprise 8.0, a commercial enterprise version.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>In 2009, Sun releases OpenSSO build 7 and 8.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>In January 2010, Sun was acquired by Oracle and development for the
      OpenSSO products were suspended indefinitely as Oracle no longer planned
      to support the product.</para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

   <para>In February 2010, a small group of former Sun employees founded ForgeRock
    to continue OpenSSO support, which was renamed as
    OpenAM.
    ForgeRock continued OpenAM's development with the following releases:</para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>2010: OpenAM 9.0</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>2011: OpenAM 9.5</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>2012: OpenAM 10 and 10.1</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>2013: OpenAM 11.0</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>2014: OpenAM 11.1 and 12.0</para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>ForgeRock continues to develop,
    enhance, and support the industry-leading OpenAM product to meet the changing
    and growing demands of the market.
   </para>
   <para>
    ForgeRock also took over responsibility for support and development of the
    OpenDS directory server, which was renamed as OpenDJ. ForgeRock plans
    to continue to maintain, enhance, and support OpenDJ.
   </para>
  </section>


 </chapter>