<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
    Copyright 2014 ForgeRock AS. All Rights Reserved.
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-objectives'
         xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
         xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
         xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook
                             http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'>
  <title>Defining Service Level Objectives</title>

  <para>
   Your deployment exists to provide service to clients and customers.
   In order to be successful, therefore, you must set your objectives
   based on what service levels you provide.
   This chapter looks at defining your objectives in terms of service levels
   including availability for different services.
  </para>

  <section xml:id="identify-services">
   <title>Identifying Key Services</title>

   <para>
    TODO: Consider the features in chap-features#server-features.
    Which of those features are critical to success for the deployment?
    (Key features are the critical ones.)
   </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="define-service-levels">
   <title>Defining Service Levels</title>

   <para>
    TODO: For each key service, consider appropriate measurements.
    For example, throughput for authn, authz decisions,
    response times for authn, authz decisions,
    average and peak levels of active sessions and tokens.
    Also discuss support levels provided to clients using key services.
    Discuss what levels of security must be provided,
    as extra network hops, HTTPS, signing and encryption, etc.
    should be taken into account when testing service performance.
   </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="define-availability-levels">
   <title>Defining Availability Levels</title>

   <para>
    TODO: For each key service, consider availability levels.
    Consider when services must be available.
    Do you really require session-level availability?
    (Users must not have to authenticate again until their session runs out.)
    Or do you only require service-level availability?
    (Users must authenticate again if session is lost.)
    Are there low usage times when services can go offline for maintenance?
    Do you require fail over across data centers?
    Or only within data centers?
    If services must be highly available, what does highly available mean
    in concrete terms?
    Define the minimum peak level at which a service is still available.
   </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="usage-expectations">
   <title>Defining Usage Expectations</title>

   <para>
    TODO: Consider the usage levels you expect,
    and for which you design the deployment.
    Consider what level of growth is manageable
    before the deployment must be expanded to meet service level expectations.
   </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="monitor-service-levels">
   <title>Monitoring Service Levels</title>

   <para>
    TODO: For each key service,
    consider how to measure uptime, throughput, response times
    at the granularity expected by clients.
    Consider how you measure and monitor usage, and how you set thresholds
    to identify when usage looks like it will soon exceed expectations.
    Consider how you monitor the production deployment
    in order to react when service levels drop below thresholds.
   </para>
  </section>
 </chapter>
