<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
    Copyright 2014 ForgeRock AS. All Rights Reserved.
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-partners'
         xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
         xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
         xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook
                             http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'>
 <title>Reaching Agreements With Partners</title>

 <para>
  When you have important dependencies on outside partners,
  you must reach agreement with them before completing your deployment.
  This chapter addresses reaching agreement with partners
  concerning federations and deployments where multiple actors share control.
  This chapter does not address business goals nor legal considerations
  though you must of course consider those aspects when planning the deployment.
 </para>

 <section xml:id="service-owners">
  <title>Working With Service Owners</title>

  <para>
   TODO: For each service owner, discuss need to agree on service levels,
   and on how the service levels will be met, monitored, supported.
   Discuss planning to meet their needs for training and documentation.
   Discuss planning for them to meet deployment service levels,
   including implementation of any changes to their service
   in order to accommodate the deployment.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="protected-applications">
  <title>Working With Application Owners</title>

  <para>
   TODO: Discuss how to understand and set expectations about service levels.
   Consider how service levels are monitored and supported.
   Discuss planning to meet their needs for training and documentation.
   Discuss how to handle agent and client application registration and profiles,
   including agent installation, dynamic registration for OpenID Connect, etc.
   Discuss how policies are defined and managed.
   Discuss delegated administration and separation of duties.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="operations">
  <title>Working With Operations</title>

  <para>
   TODO: If you own the architecture and planning,
   but others own the service in production, or even in the labs,
   you must reach agreement with those in production operations.
   Discuss planning to meet their needs for training and documentation.
   Consider how they meet service level and support needs for the deployment,
   and how service levels will be met, monitored, supported.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="build-federations">
  <title>Building Federations</title>

  <para>
   TODO: Briefly discuss circles of trust and IDP, SP, Fedlet roles.
   Consider what must be defined for transient, closed, open federations.
   Consider agreements not only on for functional aspects (roles, mappings),
   but also for implementation and testing, and for service levels.
  </para>
 </section>
<!--

 <section xml:id="build-multitenancy">
  <title>Building Multitenant Deployments</title>

  <para>
   TODO: In a multitenant deployment, you provide access management services
   to each tenant, who then administers (parts of) their own services.
   You delegate administration to tenants, and they in turn
   delegate some administration to their customers.
   Discuss ways to implement multitenancy (mainly with realms,
   though what about a large number of different tenant domains?).
   Discuss planning to meet their needs for training and documentation.
   Discuss how to tenant registration, and how to plan terms
   (realm creation, privileges, service creation, further delegation...).
   Discuss delegated administration and separation of duties.
   In a multitenant deployment, planning for growth is obviously key.
   Consider the growth implications for data stores.
   Consider the growth implications for securing OpenAM.
   Consider the growth implications for performance testing.
  </para>
 </section>
-->
</chapter>
