<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2015 ForgeRock AS.
  !
-->

<section xml:id="configure-resource-types-with-console"
          xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
          version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
          xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
          xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook
                     http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
          xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>

    <title>Configuring Resource Types by Using the OpenAM Console</title>
    <indexterm>
     <primary>Resource Types</primary>
     <secondary>Configuring</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>This section describes the process of using the OpenAM
     console for creating resource types, which
     define a template for the resources that policies apply to,
     and the actions that could be performed on those resources.</para>

    <procedure xml:id="create-resource-type-xui">

        <title>To Configure a Resource Type by Using the Policy Editor</title>

        <step>
            <para>In the OpenAM console, select Access Control &gt; <replaceable>Realm
            Name</replaceable> &gt; Policies, and then click the Resource
             Types tab.</para>
            <substeps>
             <step>
              <para>To create a new resource type, click Add New
                Resource Type.</para>
             </step>
             <step>
              <para>To modify an existing resource type, click the resource
               type name.</para>
             </step>
             <step>
              <para>To delete existing resource types, select the checkbox
               next to the name, and then click Delete Selected.</para>
              <note><para>You can only delete resource types that are not being
               used by applications or policies. Trying to delete a resource
               type that is in use will return an HTTP 409 Conflict status
               code. </para>
              <para>Remove the resource type from any associated applications or
               policies to be able to delete it.</para></note>
             </step>
             <step><para>To discard any changes and return to the previous page,
              click Cancel.</para></step>
            </substeps>
        </step>
     <step>
      <para>Provide a name for the resource type, and optionally a
       description, and then click Next.
      </para>
      <xinclude:include
       href="../shared/para-special-characters.xml"><xinclude:fallback>
       <para>
        Special Characters in Policies, Resource Types or Applications missing:
        shared/para-special-characters.xml
       </para>
      </xinclude:fallback></xinclude:include>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>To define resource patterns that policies using this
       resource type can expand upon, follow the steps below:</para>
      <substeps>
       <step>
        <para>In the Add new pattern box, enter a pattern, with
         optional wildcards, that the policies will use as a template.</para>

        <para>For information on specifying patterns for matching resources, see
         <xref linkend="policy-patterns-wildcards" />.</para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>Click the Add icon to move the pattern into
         the Patterns section.</para>
        <mediaobject xml:id="console-resource-types-patterns">
         <alt>Add the completed pattern to the Patterns section
          by clicking the Add icon.</alt>
         <imageobject>
          <imagedata
           fileref="images/console-resource-types-patterns.png"
           format="PNG" />
         </imageobject>
         <textobject><para>Add the pattern to the Patterns section.</para></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
       </step>
      </substeps>
      <tip><para>To remove a pattern,
       click the Delete icon.</para></tip>
      <para>Repeat these steps to add all the patterns your
       policy type describes, and then click Next.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>To define the actions that policies using this
       resource type can allow or deny, follow the steps below:</para>
      <substeps>
       <step>
        <para>In the Add new action box, enter an action related to the types of
         resources being described.</para>
        <para>Select either <literal>Allow</literal> or <literal>Deny</literal>
         as the default decision for the action.</para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>Click the Add icon to move the action into
         the Actions section.</para>
        <mediaobject xml:id="console-resource-types-actions">
         <alt>Add the completed resource to the Resources section
          by clicking the Add icon.</alt>
         <imageobject>
          <imagedata
           fileref="images/console-resource-types-actions.png"
           format="PNG" />
         </imageobject>
         <textobject><para>Add the resource to the Resources section.</para></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
       </step>
      </substeps>
      <tip><para>To remove an action, click the Delete icon.</para></tip>
      <para>Repeat these steps to add all the actions your
       policy type requires, and then click Next.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Review your configuration.</para>

      <tip><para>If the configuration is not visible, click the maximized
       link to switch to maximized view.</para></tip>

      <para>To make changes to the configuration, either click the relevant step,
       or click the item to jump to the relevant step and make amendments to
       the configuration.</para>

      <para>When the configuration is completed, click Finish.</para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
</section>
